Guide to the records of the Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL) M1711
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 1. Catgut Acoustical Society Collection, 1963-2007; 24.186 Linear Feet
  - Meinel, Hermann - Miscellaneous, 1934-1977; M5140-102 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    Miscellaneous: (10) Biographical material (CMH work on Benchmark; "Acoustica" article; "Lebenslauf" translation by Schelling); abstract of paper given at Budapest ICA; paper (& trans.) by Baumgartner; description of translator R.K. Walter; 1936 German newspaper describing Academy Prize; 1960 Markneukirchen Festival Program; Synthetic fiber from automatic bowing machine.
    Removed newspaper (Deutscher Reichsanzeiger, 1936) to box 60.
  - Meinel, Hermann - Technical Papers, 1936-1978; M5140-103 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    Technical: (17) Meinel's bibliography plus 16 papers. The file contains a bibliography of Meinel's work and some English translations. Topics: Response curves | wood thicknesses | varnish | tuning | violin design
  - Meyer, Erwin - Technical Papers, 1931-1938; M6120-101 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    Well known Professor of physics and researcher in acoustics, Meyer was the first to apply the electronic technology of the late 1920s and early 30s to the analysis of the tones of musical instruments, which included the violin, viola and cello. This work is published in "Die Klangspectrum der Musikinstrumente", Mitteilung aus dem Heinrich Hertz Inst. Fur Schwingungsforschung, Berlin. Walter de Gruyter U, CO. (see file)
    Technical Papers: 2 in German - English abstract - on musical instrument spectra. Topics: Spectra
    Meyer, Erwin
  - Meyer, Jürgen - Correspondence, 1969-1979; M6130-101 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    Jurgen Meyer collaborated with Werner Lottermoser and continued the work after Lottermoser's retirement from the Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt (PTB). The space serving as their anechoic chamber had been used during the war by the Luftwaffe. Subsequently assigned by the Allies for musical acoustics research, it posed some hardships requiring frequent `raking' of the floor to enhance the sound absorption properties. Meyer, a good violinist, was involved in the testing of a German violin carried out by CMH and Lottermoser. This resulted in an interesting example of regional or cultural preferences in instruments, with Meyer preferring the German violin to that of CMH, whereas Sterling Gorill, a US violinist, strongly disliked the German one. The file shows an active correspondence between JM and CMH, with his sending many reprints from his very prolific publishing. His main area of research has dealt with the directional characteristics of instruments and their effects in the symphony orchestra. He had hoped to host the ISMA '95 meeting in Braunschweig to coincide with his retirement, but the commitment had been made prior to hold the meeting in Paris.
    Correspondence between J Meyer, CMH and Michael McIntyre.
  - Meyer, Jürgen - Miscellaneous, 1977-1986; M6130-102 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous: Biographical info; ads for his books; tourist book
  - Meyer, Jürgen - Technical Papers I, 1958-1978; M6130-103.1 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    Papers on the acoustics of woodwind instruments, the pipe organ, violin, etc. List of published works.
  - Meyer, Jürgen - Technical Papers II, 1978-1993; M6130-103.2 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    Acoustics in the concert hall; auditive communication
  - Meyer, Jürgen - Book: Acoustics and the Performance of Music, 1978; M6130-104 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Minnaert, Marcel Gilles Jozef and Vlam, Christiaan Cornelis - Correspondence, 1972-1974; M6652-101 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    Correspondence of CMH with J. van Handel and C.C. Vlam to gather informatiion on M. G. J. Minnaert.
    Vlam, Christiaan Cornelis; Minnaert, M. G. J. (Marcel Gilles Jozef)
  - Minnaert, Marcel Gilles Jozef and Vlam, Christiaan Cornelis - Biographical Information and Technical Paper, 1937; M6652-102 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    Paper on the vibrations of the violin bridge
  - Moles, Abraham - Biographical Information and Technical Papers, 1959-1965; M7193-101 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    Director of The Institute of Social Psychology of Strasbourg. Concerned with study of mass media materials. Scientific advisor to The French State Radio & Television Network.
    Biographical material; Technical (2): one from Cahiers D'acoustique "Use of Sonograph in the Determination of the Quality of String Instruments", (1959) in French and a translation; one on Animal language & Information Theory, 1965 Topics: Animal language | Information theory | String inst. quality | Sonograph study
    Moles, Abraham A.
  - New Hampshire University. Violin Institute - Correspondence, 1972-1990; N5305-101 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - New Hampshire University. Violin Institute - Miscellaneous I, 1972-1992; N5305-102 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    Course announcements, news clippings, brochures, campus information.
  - New Hampshire University. Violin Institute - Miscellaneous II, 1978-1980; N5305-103 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    Summer Workshops 1978 - 1980: Notes, some financial records, possible essay questions and course outline, lists of registered students, correspondence with students, completed registration forms and course announcements for seminars in violin acoustics given by CMH at the Violin Institute.
  - Pasqualini, Gioacchino - Correspondence, 1955-1973; P2840-101 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    A concert violinist also trained in mathematics and acoustics (receiving his diploma from the University of Rome in 1938) Pasqualini maintained a lifelong interest in the art and science of violin making as well as the study of ancient instruments. As sponsor and contributor to many national and international conferences in violin acoustics, Pasqualini did much to engender the revival of violin making in Italy, and was a prime influence in the reestablishment of the Cremona Violin Making School. His research in electroacoustics applied to the study of violin acoustics and his extensive correspondence on the subject brought Pasqualini a worldwide reputation. He corresponded with F.A. Saunders and C.M. Hutchins. He was especially interested in standardizing the size of the viola at 16 1/2 inches. In 1962 he presented his extensive collection of stringed instruments to the Saint Cecilia Academy of Rome in memory of his son who died tragically. Pasqualini is best known today in violin acoustics for his joint paper with Italo Barducci, "Misura dell'attrito interno at delle constanti elastiche del legno" Il Nuovo Cimento, 5(5), 16-466 (1948) reproduced in Benchmark Vol. 5 with English translation.
    Letters involving REF, CMH, Pasqualini, and FAS.
    Pasqualini, Gioacchino
  - Pasqualini, Gioacchino - Miscellaneous I, 1951-1969; P2840-102 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    Biographical material, bibliographic publications, `homages' to G.P.
  - Pasqualini, Gioacchino - Miscellaneous II, P2840-103.1 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    A.N.L.A.I (Nat'l Assoc Italian Luthiery) statutes & notices; bibliographies on ultrasound; programs from 2nd & 3rd nat'l competitions for contemporary makers; competition announcements; newspaper accounts.
  - Pasqualini, Gioacchino - Miscellaneous III, 1954-1955; P2840-103.2 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    Satnta Cecila Journal; Publications (2) of the Istituto Nazionale di Ultracustica O.M. Corbino
  - Pasqualini, Gioacchino - Technical Papers, 1948-1961; P2840-104 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    Technical papers: (5) with some translations. Also a translation of an article by Pasqualini, but probably based on one by Chisto Petkov.
  - Payne, Roger - Miscellaneous, 1967-1972; P3465-101 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    Clippings and articles (2) on Payne's research on whales
    Payne, Roger
  - Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata - Miscellaneous, 1970-1972; R1652-101 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    The early work of C V Raman, Nobel laureate in physics, 1930, included significant work in musical acoustics, primarily on the physics of the bowed string. His interests later shifted to optics. Detailed biographical data is to be found in file 101. Although contact with him began initially with F A Saunders, this correspondence file (102) begins in 1963 with J C Schelling's attempts to locate Raman's significant paper on the Mechanical Theory of Vibrations of Bowed Strings ... (included in 103). In 1968 CMH offered Raman an honorary membership in the CAS. His gracious acceptance will be found in the correspondence file (102). Locating his papers proved to be a fairly difficult task as the correspondence indicates; since those days, his collected works have been edited by B S Ramakrishna and published by the Indian Academy of Sciences. See the Technical Summary for the reference.
    Obits: NY Times, J of Optical Soc of America & A H Benade for CASNL #15 Biogs: Brochure from centenary tribute & drafts by CMH. Book Reviews: (1) `The Raman Effect. Vol 1 Principles' by Anthony Anderson from Physics Today, Dec 1972; (2) `Journey into Light: Life and Science of C V Raman' by G Venkataraman from Physics Today, Dec,1989. Quotation: from `Chandra', a biography of Raman's nephew by Kameshwar C Wali.
    Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata, Sir
  - Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata - Correspondence, 1963-1995; R1652-102 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    Correspondence involving Raman, J C Schelling, CMH, Martin Benade, D Haines & others in India on subjects of search for and permission to reprint papers of Raman, and honorary membership in the CAS for Raman. Subsequent to his death in 1970 the correspondence between CMH, Edward Carterette, D K Pathak and B S Ramakrishna deals with the celebration of his birth centenary in Bangalore, and the publication of his collected works.
  - Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata - Technical Papers I, 1911-1920; R1652-103.1 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    Technical: Table of contents for collected works of C V Raman; Copies of 6 papers; 2 bulletins from the Indian Association for the Cultivation of Science. See Technical Summary for titles. Topics: Bowed string; mechanical bowing.
  - Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata - Technical Papers II, 1920; R1652-103.2 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    Paper (1) on experiments with mechanically played violins
  - Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata - Technical Papers III, 1957-1988; R1652-104 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    Papers by others stemming from Raman's work: 5 papers by Kar, Dutta, Ghosh, Bagchi extracted from Indian J of Physics. 1 paper by Caterette written for Raman' centenary. Topics: Bowed string, Raman & music perception
  - Reder, Otto - Correspondence, 1963-1978; R3140-101 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    An engineer, born in Madrid, living in Germany, Bremen-Lesum and then Baden-Baden. He had followed the writings of F.A.Saunders and was much interested in the construction and acoustics of violins. He was very good at getting people together and working with others; in the 1960s introduced CMH and Schelleng to Prof Werner Lottermoser of the PTB in Braunschweig who had been researching violins for many years; also to Dr. Jurgen Meyer who was at that time Lottermoser's assistant; made possible an exchange of free violin plates for tuning as well as a completed violin for comparative tests between Schelleng-CMH and Lottermoser-Meyer with many records of the effects of changes. Reder had violins made by meister Hans Klotz of Mittenwald and Dietrich Liebenwein of Baden-Baden with records on plate tones etc. and compiled free plate mode frequencies of many violins. He made possible a good visit with Fernando Solar, violin maker, in Madrid. Otto Reder was an enthusiastic member of the CAS, attended the first Mittenwald Symposium and wrote for the NEWSLETTER. Ill health prevented him from travelling to the USA.
    Correspondence involving Virginia Apgar, CMH, W Lottermoser, Erna Reder, Otto Reder, F A Saunders and J C Schelleng.
    Reder, Otto
  - Reder, Otto - Miscellaneous, 1959-1970; R3140-102 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    Biog info; diagrams, brochures, charts. Technical: CASNL #13 `The Search for the Perfect Bow'. Topics: Bows | plate testing | violin acoustics.
  - Reinicke, Friedrich Ludwig Walter - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1973-1978; R3720-101 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    A student of Professor Lothar Cremer at the Heinreich Hertz Institute in Berlin who, with Cremer made the first interferometric holograms of the completed vibrating violin. He subsequently did the first definitive analysis of the violin and cello bridges using hologram interferometry for his Doctoral thesis (included here). His article on this :"Transfer Characteristics of Stringed Instrument Bridges" in the CAS NL #19 is a summary report of the thesis and has been invaluable to many researchers (translated by Dr Edward Wall with Reinicke's approval). Since 1973 Reinicke has been a staff member in the acoustical consulting office of Muller BBN-GmbH, Munich.
    Reinicke, Friedrich Ludwig Walter
  - Reinicke, Friedrich Ludwig Walter - Biography and Technical Papers, 1970-1978; R3720-102 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Biography; Technical: (1) `Application of Holographic Interferometry to Vibrations of the Bodies of String Instruments', with L.Cremer, JASA 10/70; (2) Doctoral thesis, Berlin 1973 `Die Ubertragungseigenschaften des Streichinstrumentensteges'; (3) Extract in German of Thesis in CASNL 19 5/73; (4) Translation by E Wall; (5) `Transfer Characteristics of Stringed Instruments Bridges' from CAS NL 29 5/78. Topics: Holography | Bridges
  - Richter, Elizabeth - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1969-1987; R5350-101 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    A Juilliard graduate and professional string player (violin, viola, cello) who was very active in promoting chamber music groups, especially informal ones for her many students and fiddling associates, where she was wonderful at encouraging and developing a real feel for the glorious literature of chamber music. She owned and played a Steiner cello and violin inherited from her father. She was most helpful to CMH in comparing the tonal qualities of various instruments. Libby moved from nearby West Orange to Valdosta, Georgia in 1985.
    Correspondence; Announcements & articles on Chamber Music Bashes held at Pleasantdale Farms in West Orange 1969-1973.
    Richter, Elizabeth
  - Risset, Jean-Claude - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1968 - 1976; R5960-101 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    A physicist with a D es Sc from the university of Paris, who is also a pianist and composer, Risset has done much definitive work in the analysis and synthesis of speech and musical tones and computer composition. He was first associated with the Centre Nationale de la Recherche Scientifique and then came to the Bell Laboratories, Murray Hill in the 1960s during which time he became interested in the research of the CAS and the Octet instruments. His paper with M.V. Mathews "Analysis of Musical-Instrument Tones", Physics Today Vol. 22 No. 2 gives the evolution in time of the onset of 13 harmonics for the first 0.2 sec of a trumpet tone. Risset tried to do this for a violin tone, but found the violin tones too variable. In 1972 Risset wrote that he had a position at University d'Aix in Marseille where he was developing a research center in musical acoustics and computer music. He was also at IRCAM in Paris.
    Correspondence; Research in France (Leipp & Bladier); Miscellaneous: Tourist map of France
    Risset, Jean-Claude
  - Risset, Jean-Claude - Technical, 1966; R5960-102 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    Technical: Memo from BTL 1966 - Computer study of Trumpet Tones. Topics: Trumpet Tones | Sound Perception | Computer analysis
  - Rohloff, Ernst - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1972-1983; R7385-101 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Dr. Ernst Rohloff studied mathematics at the University of Berlin and Braunschweig. He had many technical interests and was also a violin soloist and an art painter. His study with F. Kruger on the internal damping of wood for violins sparked a great deal of interest at the time when it was published in 1938. He subsequently did more work along these lines, some of the papers are included in the collection and some are in the Benchmark Volumes, I and II, along with a biographical sketch of him and the work he did. He corresponded with C. Hutchins considerably in the preparation of the Benchmark Volumes and on his research in general. He studied the violin in a vacuum and was particularly interested in the speaking qualities of violins.
    Rohloff, Ernst
  - Rohloff, Ernst - Technical Papers, 1940-1964; R7385-102 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    List of works; abstract on article, Speaking of Violin Sounds; photograph of Rohloff's research equipment; reprints of published articles.
  - Ruiz, Pierre M. - Technical, 1969; R9340-101 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    Ruiz's paper on a technique for stimulating the vibrations of strings with a digital computer done at the Bell Telephone Laboratories in 1969. Results of the analyses were presented in the form of graphs via a Stromberg-Carlson 4020 Microfilm plotter and the sound syntheses recorded on tape. (NSF grant work started under L Hiller at Univ. of Ill. and completed at Bell Labs) Topics: String vibrations | Computer simulation
    Ruiz, Pierre Michel
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1960-1963; S2570-101.1 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    This group evolved slowly. After CMH had finished her first viola in 1949 (the only one she planned to make) Louise Rood (Professor of viola at Smith College who played chamber music with FAS) and Helen Rice (of Amateur Chamber Music Players fame) introduced her and the viola to Saunders. He looked the instrument all over, tapped it, blew in the f-holes and said "Young lady I shall be interested in your next one." He gave CMH several reprints which indicated that he had never made any drastic changes to the violins he studied. So CMH offered to make one that he could cut up. This worked so well, she made several more. Saunders did over 300 tests on these using mainly his "loudness test" (see Notebooks). Shipping instruments back and forth from Montclair to South Hadley with suggestions for experiments gradually developed into quite a program over the next ten years, with CMH adding her ideas for tests and changes. The violas in the experiments and the regular ones she was making during this time were checked twice a year with Helen Rice's musical friends who met in Stockbridge, MA or in NYC. R E
    Fryxell, a chemist, who was the cellist in the Stockbridge gatherings, became very much interested in the experimental instruments and visited Saunders several times. From these discussions Fryxell started doing some research on properties of wood for violins. After J C Schelleng's retirement from Bell Labs he contacted Saunders on the acoustics of the cello, and was subsequently introduced to CMH who lived near him. This started a long and fruitful interchange between Saunders, Schelleng, Fryxell and CMH on violin research. The early correspondence was not kept, but the lively interchange between Schelleng, Fryxell, Saunders and Hutchins from 1961 through 1965 is in Files 101 and 102. It was during this time that the Catgut Acoustical Society (a name jokingly suggested by Schelleng) was formally started just a few days before Saunders died on June 9, 1963.
    Correspondence during South Hadley period. Numerous letters each year, except from 1954-55. Replies by Carleen Hutchins were made by postcard and were not preserved.
    Saunders, Frederick A. (Frederick Albert)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1955-1959; S2570 - 101.2 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1950-1953; S2570 - 101.3 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Miscellaneous, 1963-1966; S2570 - 102 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    Biography and obituary materials. Tributes by Louise Rood, Carleen Hutchins, John Schelling, and Harvard faculty; newspaper obits; Saunders' will; program of memorial services at Harvard and Mount Holyoke College; photos in Harvard lab, in south Haley, and with Jascha Heifetz.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Technical Papers, 1937-1966; S2570 - 103 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Published papers (15). Topics: Strad secrets; Curtis String Quartet; air tones; tap tones; mechanical action.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Memorial Concert I, 1966; S2570 - 104.1 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    Materials on Saunders' Memorial Concert June 3, 1966 at Harvard, played on Hutchins' violin octet; invitations, grant application; program preparations; fund raising; reviews; photos.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Memorial Concert II, 1966; S2570 - 104.2 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    Saunders' Memorial Concert: contributions and acknowledgments from attendees.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Memorial Concert III, 1966; S2570 - 104.3 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence, 1959-1975; S2570 - 105 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between Carleen Hutchins, Mrs. Margaret T. Saunders, and Saunders' daughter Peggy S. Middleton.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Proposal for the Saunders Institute, 1970; S2570 - 106 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Proposal submitted to the Dean of Engineering at MIT, Jan. 1970. Outline of objectives, required facilities, and budget. Institute was to be dedicated to the research on acoustical properties of violin type musical instruments.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1935-1937; S2570 - 201.1 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1938; S2570 - 201.2 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1938-1939; S2570 - 201.3 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1939; S2570 - 201.4 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1940; S2570 - 201.5 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1940; S2570 - 201.6 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence on Acoustics at Vassar College and Mount Holyoke College, 1936-1938; S2570 - 203 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from Harvard, 1941; S2570 - 201.7 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence Acoustical Society of America, 1936-1940; S2570 - 202.1 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    General business and regarding membership with Wallace Waterfall.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence Acoustical Society of America, 1936-1940; S2570 - 202.2 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from South Hadley, 1942-1949; S2570 - 204.1 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from South Hadley, 1950-1953; S2570-204.2 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from South Hadley, 1954-1959; S2570-204.3 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from South Hadley I, 1960-1963; S2570-204.4 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence from South Hadley II, 1960-1963; S2570-204.5 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Correspondence Personal, 1939-1962; S2570-205 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    Personal: musical friends, such as Louise Rood, Helen Rice and Florence D. Smith; household and business letters.
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Miscellaneous, 1938-1962; S2570-301 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    Newspaper articles; maps; newsletters of Wm Moening & Sons
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Magazine: Violin and Violinists, 1938-1958; S2570-302 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Book: College Physics, 1960; S2570-401.1 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Book: A Survey of Physics, 1934; rt215mg9697 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Saunders, Frederick Albert - Figures and diagrams for book: A Survey of Physics, xb880zd9992 (Box 42, Folder 2)